<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Oppugnation and fierce siege of Ostend by  the Arch-duke Albertus his forces, commanded by the Duke of Ossuna, who came before the said towne, the fift day of Iune last past (after their writing) shewing what hath hapned since the time of the saide siege.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08573</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143264</idno>
  <idno type="VID">28342</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240919480</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 18892.7</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S3283</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28342)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1881:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Oppugnation and fierce siege of Ostend by  the Arch-duke Albertus his forces, commanded by the Duke of Ossuna, who came before the said towne, the fift day of Iune last past (after their writing) shewing what hath hapned since the time of the saide siege.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>V.S. for T. Pavier,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page lacking. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Ostend (Belgium) --  History --  Siege, 1601-1604.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:28342:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28342:1"/>
            <head>The Oppugnation and fierce siege of Ostend, <hi>by the Arch-duke</hi> Albertus his Forces, commanded by the Duke of Ossuna, who came before the said Towne, the fift day of Iune last past (after their writing) shewing what hath hapned since the time of the saide siege.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Stend</hi> is a Towne scituated on the Flemish coast, lying on the arme of the riuer <hi>Y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perle,</hi> thorowe which the weast Sluice lately ranne into the sea, and hath there made a sufficiēt tide hauen, which (like as, for the most parte, all the rest of the Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish hauens, doe ebbe and flowe: and can not be vsed but with an high water, or at the least wise, at halfe flood) doth notwithstanding conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually holde, and containe the ditches of the Towne full of water, by reason of Dammes and Sluces made to that end and purpose, which (forasmuch as it might be in the same course continued, returned, or perhappes by the ennemy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted) they of the Towne haue, of themselues, stopped the course thereof, whereby they of the Country of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> haue béene forced to carry and conuey the same by the Forte of <hi>Albertus,</hi> and so by a new currant into the Sea.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28342:2"/>
            <p> In times past, it was but an open village, yet reasonable great, and well peopled. First, after the comming of <hi>Don Iohn d'Austria,</hi> in the beginning of the nowe warres, for the fitte and commodious scituation thereof, it was made a Towne, and enuironed with strong walles: And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, this Towne only, and none others among all the rest of the sea townes of <hi>Flaunders</hi> remayned, and at this present doth remayne in the possession or amitie of the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted prouinces of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeland,</hi> howbeit, it lieth in the middle (as it were) of the ennemies Countrie, and farre from her friendes. And yet maugre all the forces, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of her enuironing foes, hath many times béene valiantly defended against sundry besiegings and attempts.</p>
            <p>For in the yéere <hi>1583.</hi> although the duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> with his victorious hoste (after he had taken <hi>Dunkerk,</hi> and <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> the next adioyning sea Townes westward) didde in most furious maner besiege it, vsing all warlike meanes hée coulde possible to conquer it, was forced to giue place, and after that he had continued his siege fiue dayes, sawe how bootelesse it was for him to spend any longer time about it, and therefore departed, not effecting any thing agreeable to his wished attempts.</p>
            <p>Afterwardes, in the yeere <hi>1585.</hi> although <hi>Monsieur la Motte</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Graueling,</hi> did, with great force and difficultie winne the olde Towne by the Strand or sea side, which at that time was onely defended with a simple wall, or <hi>Raueling</hi> and <hi>Pallisados,</hi> with purpose there presently to intrench and defend himselfe, was againe with all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, like shéepe driuen out of the same, leauing behind him fortie of his principallest Captaynes and Commaunders with all their furniture and prouision.</p>
            <p>This Towne, without all question, is a place of great aduantage, and importaunce, yea of such moment, that it serueth as a bulwarke and strong defence, for the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Zeland,</hi> and so contrariwise, if it shoulde fall into
<pb facs="tcp:28342:2"/>the enemies hands (as God forbid) he should thereby com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund a more fitte and commodious hauen for shipping, than any other sea Towne nowe in his possession can yeelde him. Yea our intollerable losses, not to be recouered doe teach vs, and as it were, with a finger poynt vnto vs, what inestimable domage might redound vnto the vnited Prouinces, if the enemy should commaund in this Town.</p>
            <p>Further, it is to be noted, that the Country of <hi>Flaunders,</hi> beeing in peace, in all taxations of the seauentéene Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces did leuy the third peny: whereunto they haue béene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by this Towne, not only during the time of these wars, but also, the greatest part of the maine land hath béene con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strained many yéeres, to pay toll and contribution, and to be vnder our deuotion.</p>
            <p>For which causes, this Towne hath with great care and mighty charges of the vnited Prouinces bin daily fortified, and continually strengthned, and especially in the yéere <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> past <hi>1600.</hi> as also in the fore parte of this present summer: many workes, I say, haue béene deuised to withstand, and preuent the cruell attempts of the bloody ennemy, as bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes, counterpoynts, and Rauelings to the landward, neither hath that part lying to the Sea beene forgotten, but hath béene made also very defencible with heades, bankes, and ditches, and especially on the east side of the Towne where (by meanes of the weakenesse of the bankes) the sea, with great force is mightly broken into the land, where it hath skowred, and pierced a great depth; so that the chanel of the new hauen (when the water is lowest) is neere twoo, pikes déepe: and doth daily waxe deeper and deeper, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt, the determinate worke of God, for the great strengthning and playne defence of the Towne.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Flaunders</hi> generally finding what annoyaunce and great discommoditie this Towne threatned daily vnto them, haue solicited and by all meanes possible importuned their Gouernours, to besiege, and conquer this Towne of
<pb facs="tcp:28342:3"/>
               <hi>Ostend,</hi> their daily eie-sore: as of late yéeres (yet fresh in memorie) in the yeare <hi>1596.</hi> after that the Archduke <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus</hi> had taken the Towne of <hi>Callice,</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> they required him then to take in hand this péece of worke, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mising to giue him twelue hundred thousand gilderns with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thrée moneths time (which in sterling money is one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty thousand poundes) wherevnto, after his Highnesse had made shew to yéelde, and promised to fulfil their desire, he gote some parte of the summe aforesayde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his handes. But doubting the euent of the attempt, or knowing howe hard a matter it was, to take it by force of armes, or how difficult it woulde be to constraine the souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers thereof by hunger, or otherwise, thought it sufficient to shew himselfe before the Towne with his forces, and so qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly to departe.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Flaunders</hi> herewith nothing at all pleased, and gréeued with the continuall vexations and incursions of the ranging souldiers, and payment of contributions, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the same, in the yéere of our Lord <hi>1599.</hi> while our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were imployed in the defence of <hi>Bommel,</hi> had good ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to make sundry forts and bulwarkes, for the strengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp; defence of the wayes and passages about the towne of <hi>Ostend,</hi> thereby (as it were with a small kinde of siege) continually to trouble the Towne, and to hinder the incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of the garison: which deuice was put into their heads, and the plotte layde downe by a certaine Corporall of the Towne called <hi>Noel,</hi> who hauing before long serued in the towne, and hauing good experience of the secrets thereof, vppon some discontentment receiued, forsooke the Towne, and ran to the seruice of the enemy.</p>
            <p>But as the experience of the last yeare giueth sufficient proofe, that all the strength of these Fortes is not able to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or defend the entrance of an Hoste, so also it is most ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest that by the continuall charge of the Garrisons of these Fortes, the Country hath receiued more domage and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoditie,
<pb facs="tcp:28342:3"/>then before it did by the contribution to their enemies, and Towne of <hi>Ostend;</hi> wherefore they haue béen forced to renewe their Importunate sute vnto his Highnes, and to sollicit him againe to the besieging of <hi>Ostend,</hi> and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially at this instant, knowing our forces to be remoued farre from them, and to be sent into Dutchland lying at the siege of <hi>Berck,</hi> where they should (as they imagined) haue long worke: And for the better perswading, and more easily drawing of the Archouke to harken to this their sute, haue promised to pay him extraordinarily, thrée hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand gilderns Monthly (which is <hi>30</hi> thousand pounds star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) during the time of the siege, and after the taking of the towne to pay him farther (for the space of two years) ninety thousand gilderns euery month (which is <hi>9000.</hi>l starling.</p>
            <p>Hereupon th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>Archduke gathred together al his souldiers: yea such as were about the riuer of <hi>Ryne</hi> &amp; the <hi>Mase,</hi> for the succor of <hi>Berck</hi> were sent for, to make their repaire into <hi>Flaunders</hi> and to serue vnder the commaund of the Duke of <hi>Osluna,</hi> who not long since was to that end sent for out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> by reason that the Archdukes campe (thorow the long imprisonment of the <hi>Admirant</hi> of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and the last ouerthrowe in <hi>Flaunders</hi>) was wholy left destitute and vnprouided of a sufficient Commaunder, and experient Leaders, and for that the naturall Lordes of the land, are in no wise respected nor trusted.</p>
            <p>VPon the fift day of Iune (after the new stile) the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie came before <hi>Ostend,</hi> about noone, with eight re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments of footmen, which were eight thousand men strong, besides the horsemen (notwithstanding the Spaniards ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally disliked of this enterprise, and counselled the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who (as is reported) do wholly dislike of this siege: and among the rest, twoo common souldiers that hadde béene the last yeare prisoners in <hi>Ostend,</hi> obstinately maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the inuincible strength of this Towne, were presently
<pb facs="tcp:28342:4"/>taken and hanged: for the extreame want of the thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand gilderns, to be payed monthly, as before is saide, comming very fitly for the payment of the mutined souldiers, and also the hope to drawe our forces from the siege of <hi>Bercke,</hi> into <hi>Flanders,</hi> for the better furnishing of him selfe, &amp; presenting of such wants as might happen to <hi>Ost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end:</hi> and perhaps thinking sodainly, and with al his force to ouercharge the towne before it should be succored, haue bin the lesons to bring thArchdukes forces now before <hi>Ostend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Ossuna</hi> presently sought to pacifie the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison of <hi>Issabella,</hi> which had before mutined for their pay: and the next day folowing, being the sixt day of Iuly, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted six péeces of ordonance against the east side of the towne vpon the Downes, and with the same beganne fiercely to play vpon the Towne.</p>
            <p>There were then in the towne in garrison one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ancients of sundry Regiments, and one company of Burgers, or Townesmen, all vnder the direction and commaund of Captayne <hi>Vander Noote.</hi> These presently prepared themselues to their defence, making harmelesse, and displacing some of the enemies artillerie: And labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hard, to make a new way or hauen, betweene the heads, to the end the passage of boates and shipping might be frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the ordonaunce of the ennemy.</p>
            <p>And the ninth day of Iuly, after that they had sent away the most parte of their wiues and children, they receiued into the towne (out of <hi>Zeland</hi>) <hi>28.</hi> cōpanies of souldiers, with great abundance of victuals, and all other prouision of war.</p>
            <p>The tenth day sir <hi>Frances Vere,</hi> with eight companies of Englishmen entred into the Towne also, who presently issued out of the Towne with his people, entrenching him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe on the drie plottes of ground next vnto the walles, on the west side, from whence the enemy might haue endo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maged the towne, and battered the walles.</p>
            <p>The thirtéenth day of Iuly, the sayde sir <hi>Frances Vere;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:28342:4"/>with great force and resolution sallied vpon the enemy with eight hundred men, on the west parte of the towne, and set vpon the Campe, which lay farre off diuided from each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with waters and marish grounds, and can not easily, or in short time come to ayde each other. In which sally, the ennemy lost (as was certified by Letters from <hi>Antwerpe</hi>) aboue eight hundred men, and among the same, one cornet of horsemen: and, if the whole force of the ennemies horse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, had not the sooner come to their ayde, it was most ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant to all mens iudgements, that sir <hi>Frances</hi> had dro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the footemen to great confusion, and taken from them their Ordonance.</p>
            <p>The fiue and twentieth day sir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> did agayne issue out of the Towns with fifteene hundred men, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to intrench betwéene <hi>Issabella</hi> and <hi>Grootendorst,</hi> on a high ground, which in times past was an old Churchyard, where they of <hi>Issabella</hi> and <hi>Grootendorst</hi> were accustomed to bury their dead, and is a very fitte and apt place, to sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and cutte off these two Fortes from each others helpe, and to open a faire way to those of <hi>Ostend,</hi> to the flatte and plaine land. To which place of buriall, the next day, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the sixe and twentieth day of Iuly, the ennemy came with thrée thousand men, and after hée had béene thrice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulsed, and put to the woorst, tooke the place, but was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently with great force and dexteritie driuen from it agayne.</p>
            <p>The same day tenne companies of souldiers arriued at <hi>Ostend,</hi> and were receiued into the Towne, which were sent thither by her Maiestie from <hi>London,</hi> so that now the Towne was furnished (within the walles and without) with sixtie and seauen companies, which made vp neere the number of seuen thousand men: these tenne companies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresayde, were presently employed against the enemy, who shewed themselues very valorous, and did, both then, and since, passing good seruice, although many men were of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, that they would prooue vnfitte for any seruice, by
<pb facs="tcp:28342:5"/>reason they were rawe, and had not beene trayned.</p>
            <p>On the other side, the Archduke daily strengtheneth and encreaseth his Campe, as well with souldiers, as with ordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, playing continually on the west side with <hi>26.</hi> péeces, and on the east side with nine péeces of ordonance, but most of his shotte liteth vppon the houses, whereof many are defaced and beaten downe: For, this sixe and twentieth day of Iuly, and before, there had beene discharged vppon the Towne sixteene thousand shot, and against the ennemie from the Towne had béene counterchanged six thousand.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, there were also receiued into the Campe some parte of the new souldiers which came out of <hi>Italie,</hi> and had béene appoynted for the succour of <hi>Berke,</hi> for first there arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued eight hundred men of those companies, and afterwards fiue and twenty hundred more were sent for, part Italians, and part Spaniards: and besides these, xx. men more out of all the other Ancients vnder the gouernment of the Erle of <hi>Barlamont</hi> and <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> who, for this cause, were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to discharge their wagons, and other prouisions, before by them taken vp, and meant to be vsed in raising the siege before <hi>Bercke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are eightéene companies appoynted euery night out of the Towne, to garde sir <hi>Frances Veres</hi> trenches on the southwest parte of the Towne, who daily falleth out vppon the ennemy, with other souldiers of the Towne, and haue oftentimes slayne many of the ennemies, &amp; wounded more, which haue béene sent to <hi>Bruges</hi> from the Campe, so that their No pitalles are full of wounded souldiers, and many Captaines, and men of great accompt, aswell Spaniardes, Italians, and others, haue béene slaine in these conflictes, and amongest the rest, a Colonell of the Spaniardes was brought to <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> and there first buryed in his armour, and afterwardes taken vp againe, and put into the earth in a Friars weede, with great solempnitie.</p>
            <p>On Sonday, being the sixe and twentieth day of Iuly
<pb facs="tcp:28342:5"/>last past, was a great skirmish with the ennemy, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued very long, and was with great furie, valour, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution maintained on both sides, the ennemy supplying his s<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>lers with fresh companies, bringing thrée, foure, and fiue companies at a time, and they of the Towne seconding their parte continually with newe supplies, and with like numbers, so that in the end, it seemed rather a little battell, than a shirmish, sometime our people being ouermatched with the fresh companies of their ennemies, were forced to giue ground: but presently againe, with their new supplies from the Towne, couragiously pressed into the thickest of the enimies, making them likewise to retire into their trenches: and thus it continued long, sometimes the one parte, and sometimes the other giuing ground, vntill the ennemies horsemen came in, to succour their footemen, wherevppon our men returned into their trenches, and into the Lowne, after they had slaine and spoiled many of their enemies both horse and foote. But if our men had béene furnished with horsemen, the ennemy had lost many more men than hée did, both in this skirmish, and all others before: but héere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the enemy hath had the vantage of vs during this siege, notwithstanding it hath béene written from <hi>Callice,</hi> that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this fight, there were carried out of the Campe to <hi>Bruges</hi> thrée score and ten wagons laden with wounded men, and in euery wagon was tenne men at the least: but when they were brought to <hi>Bruges,</hi> they of the Towne woulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, saying that they had their Hospitalles alreadie full, and coulde receiue no more, and therefore required that they might be conueyed to some other townes. It was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes reported, that the ennemy lost in this skirmish <hi>450.</hi> men, besides those that were wounded: neyther was this attempt accomplished, without losse on our side.</p>
            <p>Saterday, being the first day of this present moneth of August, they of the Towne issued againe vpon the ennemy, and with great furie (after they had continued skirmish som
<pb facs="tcp:28342:6"/>halfe houre) forced them to retire to their trenches, slaying some <hi>80.</hi> of their enemies, as néere as could be iudged: but the horsemen of the enemy comming in vpon our souldiers, they returned into the Towne, with small losse on our part.</p>
            <p>It is reported by some that came very lately from <hi>Callice,</hi> that on wednesday last, being the fift day of this present mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of August, there was a great Skirmish begunne by those of the Towne, to hinder the enemies approach vnto the walles, which was with fierce resolution long continued on both sides, and that they of the towne (with great slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their enemies) had taken thrée or fiue péeces of ordo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and brought the same into the Towne, but how cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this is (being but a reporte) I cannot write, the trueth thereof will be hereafter better knowne.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> without the Towne doth daily fortify his trenches: and the Gouernour within the Towne, with earth raiseth the walles, thereby to auoyde the daunger of the enemies shot, which his Highnesse spareth not, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoweth so liberally vpon the Towne, as if he found shot and powder aboundauntly in the Downes, or sand-hilles: and withall, laboreth to raise a new Cauallirie, with bauen and earth, thereon to plant more ordonaunce, and to shoote in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Towne, on the south southwest side. Thus they are earnestly busied on all sides, the one, nor the other sparing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cost or labor to annoy their enemy, and to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, and that thing which to day is not thought vpon, is the next day put in practise, with new deuises and warlike stratagems, the one raising vp, the other with his ordonance beating downe his ennemies works, that the same may not be finished, or brought to perfection.</p>
            <p>It is also written from <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> that the <hi>Infanta</hi> is in person come into the Campe, and that the Archduke is in <hi>O udenburgh,</hi> to the end he may himselfe in person giue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in these affaires: time will teach vs to knowe what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite hée shal reape by these his trauels &amp; inestimable charges.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28342:6"/>
            <p> But at her returne from the Camp to <hi>Bruges,</hi> shée broght with her sundry Companies of Souldiers, but they of the Towne denyed to receiue them, saying they had no néede of any new Garrison, but if it pleased her highnes to come into the Towne with her accustomed trayne, shée should be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: but as for her Souldiers, they were not minded to take them into the Cittie.</p>
            <p>Such as haue come out of <hi>Ostend</hi> very lately, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise from <hi>Vlushing,</hi> reporte for certaine, that within the Towne of <hi>Ostend,</hi> there wanteth not any thing, fit for the defence thereof, and that all victualles are very plentifull, English béere is solde for twoo stiuars the kanne, great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, for which there is no excise payde. Sir <hi>Frances Vere</hi> giueth the enemie daily so much to doe, and kéepeth him so well occupied, that he knoweth not well which way to turne him, or what hée may well beginne to annoy the Towne: and it is thought by many men of good iudgement, that hée wisheth he had not come to besiege <hi>Ostend,</hi> séeing he findeth so small hope to carry it, but would rather be with his camp from thence, if he knew how with credite to departe.</p>
            <p>Lately the enemy remooued nine péeces of his ordonance, from the east to the weast side: his ordonance made it verie dangerous to enter by the accustomed hauen, except it were in the night time, but since the making of the last, or middle hauen, all things are carried in and out without any daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the enemies shot. And on the southwest side the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my bringeth great store of brush and bauen fagots towards the trenches of sir <hi>Frances Vere,</hi> thinking by that meanes so to mount some ordonaunce, that hée may beate sir <hi>Frances</hi> from his trenches, and so bring his battering péeces néerer vnto the walles, or else, to beate the Towne on the south southwest side.</p>
            <p>On the south side, the ennemy hath raised a mount, from whence hée beateth the houses, but specially the Church and Steeple, which is wholy defaced, otherwise, he doeth small
<pb facs="tcp:28342:7"/>annoyance to the Towne, sometimes with his shot killing a man: but such as come out of the Towne affirme, that for euery one the Towne looseth, the enemy looseth fiue or sixe. They of the Towne, haue themselues, vntiled and taken downe many houses, and also vnpaued the stréetes, to thend the same might with the enemies shot, the lesse annoy them.</p>
            <p>The Gouernor and sir <hi>Frances</hi> are not ydle, but employ all their labour and industrie, both within the Towne and without, to raise mounts, and to finish such other workes, as are most behoouefull for the strengthening of the Towne against the enemies forces, and to that end, such souldiers as will worke, and employ their time that way, eyther by day or night, haue xii. d. the day, and xii. d. the night.</p>
            <p>And because the enemy shall the better be kept from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proching the walles, they of the Towne haue cutte the Sea branckes, so that the Sea water enuironeth the Towne on the south side, from the east to the weast parte, in so much that the towne seemeth to stand in an Iland, which threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth great hurt to the land and countrie thereabouts, and may (in time) grewe very daungerous.</p>
            <p>The enemies perceiuing them of the towne to be very stil, and those likewise of sir <hi>Frances Veres</hi> trenches to hold them selues more quiet than they had bin accustomed, sent out a souldier to espie their doings: one of the souldiers that came from <hi>London</hi> spying this stragler, demanded of such as wer next him in the trenches, what he meant thus to approache their trenches: it was answered, they knew not, except hée came as a spie: then quoth the English souldier, I will goe out and talke with him: presently he made toward this strag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, and making but few wordes, they fell to blowes, and so continued a good space, the camp on thone side, and the town on thother, beholding them, &amp; noting which did best: In the end they were both wounded, and so departed: the English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man brought with him his enemies hat, and a staffe or halfe pike, which he valiantly won and broght into the trenches.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28342:7"/>
            <p> Since the besieging of this Towne, the fiue Gallies of <hi>Sluice</hi> were at sea, and (méeting with twoo ships laden with marchandize, which came from <hi>Dort</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> hauing a shippe of warre for their conuoy and defence) there began a hote fight on both sides, and it continued long: the shippe of warre bestowed his shot so well, that hée did great spoyle to the Gallies, and slewe many of their men, but in thend, the Gallies boorded the shippe, (and firing her) did, without mercie, put seauentie sixe men to the sworde, and saued one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ten persons, which, for the most part, are shorn, and made slaues. It was reported, that this shippe of warre was, by ouersight, set on fire with their owne powder: but by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters out of <hi>Holland,</hi> it séemeth to be otherwise, for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from thence, that it pleased God to saue one man verie myraculously, who (committing himselfe to the mercie of God, and of the mercilesse Seas, vppon a peece of a Maste) rather than hée woulde fall into the handes of his bloody en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: after hee had so floated vpon the waues of the Sea an houre or twoo, he was taken vp by an other ship, which (by Gods prouidence) had spyed the man thus driuing on the water. This man (after his comming into <hi>Holland</hi>) made true reporte héereof, as is aboue declared.</p>
            <p>Within the Towne, néere vnto the west end, they haue raised a mount, whereon is planted twelue cannons, and sixe demy cannons, wherewith they beate downe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the ennemies workes without.</p>
            <p>Lastly, such as canie on wednesday last out of <hi>Ostend,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fift day of this present August, report, that the enemie hath these eight dayes layne still, and doone nothing, and affirme, the souldiers of <hi>Ostend</hi> to be of an inuincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, not esteeming any force of the enemy, and that there is no cause of feare, nor want, for all things are daily in most plentifull sort brought vnto them, assuring themselues, that the ennemy shall (in the end) be forced to depart with shame and dishonor, and perhappes with greater losse than he now thinketh vppon, which God for his mercies sake graunt, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>